William Latham Candler Papers, 1861-1863
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
William Latham Candler Papers, 1861-1863
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1997-007
This collection has been digitized and is available online.
1 folder; 0.1 cu. ft.
The collection consists of fourteen letters, dating from September 8, 1861, to February 15, 1863, from Candler to his uncle Charles [probably maternal uncle Charles Henry Wheelwright]and his brother, John W. Candler of Boston. Candler's letters were written from camps in Maryland and Virginia.
William Latham Candler
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The William Latham Candler Papers were purchased by Special Collections in April 1997.
Alternate Form Available
This collection has been digitized and is available online.
Biographical Information
William Latham Candler of Brookline, Massachusetts, served in Company A of the 1st Massachusetts Regiment, Army of the Potomac, during the Civil War. He enlisted on May 25, 1861, as a 1st Lieutenant, and was promoted to Captain and Aide-de-Camp, U.S. Volunteers, in November 1862. He served as a captain in General Joseph Hooker's staff from November 10, 1862, until his resignation from service in May 1863.
For more information see: Cudworth, Warren H., History of the First Regiment (Massachusetts Infantry), from the 25th of May, 1861, to the 25th of May, 1864; including Brief References to the Operations of the Army of the Potomac (Boston, Walker, Fuller, and Company, 1866). Spec Civil War E513.5 1st .C88 1866
For brief biographical notes on some of the Civil War figures Candler mentions in his letters, see the list of supplemental infomation.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of fourteen letters, dating from September 8, 1861, to February 15, 1863, from Candler to his uncle Charles [probably maternal uncle Charles Henry Wheelwright] and his brother, John W. Candler of Boston.
The letters are articulate and descriptive, replete with Candler's strong opinions about the state of the Union, the abilities of the generals (Union and Confederate) who were running the war and the politicians who were running the country, and his own ambitions for advancing in rank and status in the army. On May 10, 1862, he writes from Williamsburg, Virginia, about the engagement with the Confederates and their sharpshooters. His June 24, 1962, letters from Fair Oaks, Virginia, and his July 7, 1862 letter from Harrison's Bar, Virginia, describe his units participation in the Battle of Mechanicsville, which was part of the Seven Days Campaign.
Candler's November 6, 1862, letter, written from Washington, D.C., has much about General George McClellan's political troubles, written soon before McClennan was removed from command of the Army of the Potomac and replaced by Ambrose E. Burnside. His December 21, 1862, letter disparagingly comments on the Union army's performance at the Battle of Fredericksburg, Virginia, on December 13.
Candler interspersed the letters with his concerns about the well-being of his fiance, and later, wife, Fannie, and his fear that his brother John will join the army and leave no one to care for their mother or John's children. Candler often asks his brother, a businessman in Boston, to send money.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents List
This collection has been digitized and is available online.
- Letter from Camp Union, Bladensburg, Maryland to his uncle, September 8, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp Union, Bladensburg, Maryland to his uncle, September 10, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp Union, Bladensburg, Maryland to his brother, October 22, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp Union, Bladensburg, Maryland to his brother, October 23, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp Hooker-Duncaster Charles Co., Maryland (near Budds Ferry) to his brother, November 2, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp Hooker-Lower Potomac, Maryland (near Budds Ferry) to his brother, December 8, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Office of Provost Marshall in Mayor Saunder's house in Williamsburg, Virginia, to his uncle, May 10, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Head Quarters Hooker's Div.-Camp near Fair Oaks, Virginia, to his brother, June 24, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp near Harrison's Bar, Virginia, to his brother, July 7, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp near Harrison's Landing, Virginia, to his brother, July 15, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp near James River, Virginia, to his brother, July 18, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from National Hotel in Washington, D.C., to his brother, November 6, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Camp near Potomac Creek to his brother, December 21, 1862 (Folder 1)
- Letter from Head Quarters of Army of the Potomac–Camp near Falmouth to his brother, February 15, 1863 (Folder 1)